Guide to the Herbert F. West Collection of A. Hugh Fisher
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Herbert F. West collection of A. Hugh Fisher
1860-1945
1901-1945
GEN MSS 795
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.54
(9 boxes)
The Herbert F. West Collection of A. Hugh Fisher consists of correspondence, writings, clippings, tearsheets, and fine art sent to Herbert West by the artist Alfred Hugh Fisher between 1938 and 1945. It includes over 300 letters from Fisher to West, 1938-1945; autobiographical memoirs by Fisher; volumes of travel journals (in the form of letters to his colleague Halford Mackinder) covering Fisher's work with the Visual Instruction Committee of the British Colonial Office and recording his visits to Australia, Borneo, Canada, China, Fiji, Gibraltar, Hong Kong, Japan, Malta, New Zealand, Singapore, Sri Lanka, Tasmania, and Tonga, 1907-1910; various articles, clippings, notes, manuscripts, and ephemera; and a selection of drawings, paintings, and prints by Fisher whose subjects include the home of writer Margaret Leigh, and portraits of his contemporaries Lascelles Abercrombie, Walter de la Mare, T. Sturge Moore, George W. Russell, and W. B. Yeats, among others. Also present is an etching by Hungarian printmaker Gyula (Julius) Komjati, whom Fisher visited in 1932. Although West and Fisher never met in person, their long-distance friendship gave the artist someone to whom he could entrust his work and legacy, a particularly important concern when British citizens were anticipating Germany's impending attack. In addition to describing daily life in wartime Britain, Fisher's letters to West provide further personal history and context for the material West was receiving.
West, Herbert Faulkner, 1898-1974
Komjati, Gyula, 1894-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Herbert F. West, 1954-1957; letter to Miss Pye, gift of Bertram Rota, 1958; "Lycidas" woodcuts, gift of Robert Barry, 1953.
Custodial History
West described his relationship with Fisher, and the circumstances surrounding the collection and its transfer to Yale, in an essay published in Yale University Library Gazette 29, no. 1 (July 1954): 2-8.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
West's collection of books inscribed by Fisher were cataloged separately. Fisher's letters to William Rose Benet, also a gift to the library from Herbert West, are filed in the Benet Family Papers. Albums of photographs taken by Fisher during his time with the Colonial Office Visual Instruction Committee are in the Royal Commonwealth Society Collections at the University of Cambridge Library, Cambridge, England.
Alfred Hugh Fisher (1867-1945)
Alfred Hugh Fisher, a painter, printmaker, photographer, illustrator, poet, essayist, and critic known professionally as A. Hugh Fisher and to his friends as Hugh, was born in the Brixton district of London on February 8, 1867, the son of Alfred George Fisher and Isabella Read Smith Fisher. After some schooling he obtained a position as a junior clerk at George Street & Company, an advertising agency, in 1884. As a youth Fisher had declared his intent to become an artist; he exhibited his first watercolor at the Royal Academy in 1887, and in the 1880s began his career as an illustrator for a variety of popular periodicals. He received formal art education through a scholarship awarded him by the National Art Training School (now the Royal College of Art) from 1894 to 1897, after which he studied for six months with Benjamin Constant and Jean-Paul Laurens at the Académie Julian in Paris. Beginning in 1901, Fisher traveled and worked in Europe and England, painting and drawing as well as turning out illustrations for publishers, particularly the Illustrated London News. In 1907 he was appointed to the position of artist for the British Colonial Office's Visual Instruction Committee (COVIC) under the direction of Halford Mackinder. The agency's intention was to create a series of lectures that would acquaint British children with their empire's varied geography, and Fisher was assigned to visit as many colonial possessions as he could within three years, to paint and photograph scenes to be turned into lantern slides to illustrate Mackinder's talks. His travels took him through Ceylon, India, and Burma (1907), Aden, Somaliland, Cyprus, Canada, China, Hong Kong, and Singapore (1908), Borneo, Gibraltar, Malta, and Australia (1909), and Tasmania, New Zealand, Samoa, Tonga, and Fiji (1910). In addition, a steamship accident in 1909 allowed him to spend a few days in Japan. Aside from the thousands of images he made for the committee, Fisher's journey resulted in his own volumes Through India and Burmah with Pen and Brush (1911) and India (1913). Throughout the 1920s and 1930s he regularly spent time in France, Italy, Belgium, and Germany. His friendship with the Hungarian etcher Gyula (Julius) Komjati (1894-1958), who was working in England in 1927, led Fisher to spend three months in Hungary and Czechoslovakia in 1932.
Fisher began producing etchings in the 1890s, and was elected to membership in the Royal Society of Painters and Etchers in 1898. He was also the author of The Cathedral Church of Hereford (1898), a few volumes of poetry, a novel titled Quix (1931), and many essays, obituaries, and book reviews, the latter also published under his pseudonym Caleb Reade. In 1909 Fisher married his second wife, Lilias Cecile Wyman (1875-1930), whom he had met at the offices of the Illustrated London News. He died on July 2, 1945, after having suffered a stroke, and was buried in North Curry, Somerset, England.
Herbert Faulkner West (1989-1974)
Herbert F. West, teacher, author, publisher, and Anglophile, taught comparative literature at Dartmouth College from 1925 to 1964, and was professor emeritus until his death. He received degrees from Dartmouth College and Harvard University, and founded Westholm Publications, which issued several titles between 1955 and 1972.
Scope and Contents
The Herbert F. West Collection of A. Hugh Fisher consists of correspondence, writings, clippings, tearsheets, and fine art sent to Herbert West by the artist Alfred Hugh Fisher between 1938 and 1945. It includes over 300 letters from Fisher to West, 1938-1945; autobiographical memoirs by Fisher; volumes of travel journals (in the form of letters to his colleague Halford Mackinder) covering Fisher's work with the Visual Instruction Committee of the British Colonial Office and recording his visits to Australia, Borneo, Canada, China, Fiji, Gibraltar, Hong Kong, Japan, Malta, New Zealand, Singapore, Sri Lanka, Tasmania, and Tonga, 1907-1910; various articles, clippings, notes, manuscripts, and ephemera; and a selection of drawings, paintings, and prints by Fisher whose subjects include the home of writer Margaret Leigh, and portraits of his contemporaries Lascelles Abercrombie, Walter de la Mare, T. Sturge Moore, George W. Russell, and W. B. Yeats, among others. Also present is an etching by Hungarian printmaker Gyula (Julius) Komjati, whom Fisher visited in 1932.
Although West and Fisher never met in person, their long-distance friendship gave the artist someone to whom he could entrust his work and legacy, a particularly important concern when British citizens were anticipating Germany's impending attack. In addition to describing daily life in wartime Britain, Fisher's letters to West provide further personal history and context for the material West was receiving.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1913-1954. II. Writings, Ephemera, and Photographs, 1860-1945. III. Fine Art, 1881-1941.
Artists, English -- 20th Century; Authors, English -- 20th Century; World War, 1939-1945 -- England; Australia -- Description and travel; Budapest (Hungary) -- Pictorial works; Czechoslovakia -- Description and travel; Fiji -- Description and travel; Gibraltar -- Description and travel; Hammersmith and Fulham (London, England) -- Description and travel; Hong Kong (China) -- Description and travel; Japan -- Description and travel; Malta -- Description and travel; New Zealand -- Description and travel; Singapore -- Description and travel; Sri Lanka -- Description and travel; Tasmania -- Description and travel; Tonga -- Description and travel; Drawings (visual works); Etchings (prints); Oil paintings (visual works); Photographs; Travel journals; Watercolors (paintings); Woodcuts (prints); Abercrombie, Lascelles, 1881-1938 -- Portraits; AE, 1867-1935 -- Portraits; Buday, György, 1907-1990; Bottomley, Gordon, 1874-1948 -- Portraits; Cutler, Jennie La Forge; Darwin, Erasmus Alvey, 1804-1881; De la Mare, Walter, 1873-1956 -- Portraits; Fisher, Alfred George, d. 1902; Fisher, A. Hugh (Alfred Hugh), 1867-1945; Fisher, Isabella Read Smith, 1844-1928; Fisher, Lilias Cecile Wyman, 1875-1930; Komjati, Gyula, 1894-1958; Leigh, Margaret, 1894-1973; Levy, Oscar, 1867-1946 -- Portraits; Mackinder, Halford John, 1861-1947; Milton, John, 1608-1674 ( Lycidas, Illustrations); Moore, T. Sturge (Thomas Sturge), 1870-1944; Russell, George William, 1867-1935 -- Portraits; Stephens, Frederic George, 1828-1907; West, Herbert Faulkner, 1898-1974; Whitmore, Elizabeth Manning; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939 -- Portraits; Great Britain. Colonial Office. Visual Instruction Committee
- Correspondence, 1913-1954; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: A. Hugh Fisher and Herbert F. West
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters to and from A. Hugh Fisher, with some letters between Herbert West and others. Letters to Fisher appear in the first subseries and include thirty from friends who had read his 1913 book of poems. The second subseries holds the bulk of the material, more than three hundred letters written by Fisher to West between August 1938 and June 19, 1945, two weeks before he died. Also present is correspondence with two of Fisher's friends and his American print dealer, regarding the placement of West's collection of Fisher's papers.
  Of special interest in the letters from Fisher to West is one dated March 19, 1939, enclosing the eulogy he had delivered at the memorial service held for his wife Lilias in 1931; in the letter Fisher disclosed the story of his first marriage.
  - A. Hugh Fisher
    - Letters from friends "about my first book of poems", 1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Board of Education, Trenton, New Jersey, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter and cards from György (George) Buday, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter to Miss Pye, 1924 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      General note
      Possibly Sibyl Pye (1879-1958); accompanied by three autograph manuscript sonnets: "On the Sea at Night," "A Lodging for the Night," and "Shelley," plus a typescript book review
      Removed from A. Hugh Fisher, Poems (1913); gift of Bertram Rota.
  - Herbert F. West
    - Letters from A. Hugh Fisher, 1938-1940 Aug (Box 1, Folder 5-15)
    - Letters from A. Hugh Fisher, 1940 Sep-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-29)
    - Letters from Dorothy Andrews, 1941, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence with Mary Bernhard-Smith, 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence with Elizabeth Manning Whitmore, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Writings, Ephemera, and Photographs, 1860-1945; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Writings, Ephemera, and Photographs
  Fisher had hopes that West would write his biography, and supplied him with many types of source material including his own memoirs, a mix of manuscripts, typescripts, and carbon copies. Some appear to have been written in the 1930s, but also present are the original commercial duplicate books in which Fisher recorded his COVIC observations, in the form of "diary letters" to Halford Mackinder; the volumes retain the carbon pages and, in some cases, the torn-out top sheets. Fisher's memoir of Hammersmith concentrates on his neighbors, the art critic and historian Frederic George Stephens and his family, as well as May Morris, Emery Walker, and others living nearby. Many of Fisher's letters to West (in Series I) also recount episodes of his life, so should also be consulted for biographical information. Other writings include essays, short stories, and book reviews, some of which Fisher wrote under his pseudonym of Caleb Reade.
  Ephemera contains catalogues and tickets from Fisher's exhibitions in Liverpool (1905) and London (1913), various promotional materials, clippings about his COVIC service (1907), and music by Jennie La Forge Cutler to Fisher's poem "Song of the Wind" (1914). A folder of photographs holds four snapshots and two formal portraits of Fisher; a large-format mounted photograph, taken while Fisher sat for his portrait to be carved in marble by means of a three-dimensional pantograph, is in Box 7.
  - Writings
    - Autobiographical and travel writings
      Arranged in chronological order by content
      - Timeline of life events, 1867-1945, 1939, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 33)
        See letter to West of April 4, 1939
      - Timeline of life events, 1914-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Memoir of his mother, Isabella Read Smith Fisher, 1860-circa 1939 (Box 3, Folder 35)
        Includes portrait photograph (1916) and letter from Erasmus Alvey Darwin (1804-1881) to Isabella Smith (1860)
      - Memoir of the years from 1866-1900, circa 1939 (Box 3, Folder 36)
        Includes biographical information about his father, Alfred George Fisher
      - Memoir of the years in Hammersmith, 1901-1907, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Memoir of the years in Hammersmith, 1902-1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Memoir of London, 1903-1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Journal: Ceylon, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Journal: Canada, China, Japan, Singapore, Borneo, and Canada, 1908-1909, undated (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
        Typed transcription from journal books not present in the collection
      - Journal: Hong Kong and Japan, 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Transcript of honeymoon diary kept by Lilias Fisher, June 1909, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Journal: Gibraltar and Malta, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Journal: Malta and Australia, 1909-1910 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Journal: Tasmania and New Zealand, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Journal: New Zealand and Tonga, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Journal: Tonga and Fiji, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Journal: Fiji and Australia, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Journal: Australia, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Notes on travels in Hungary and Czechoslovakia, 1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 52-53)
      - Miscellaneous memoirs, 1903-1925 (Box 5, Folder 54)
        Includes "About George Moore"
    - Other writings
      - Book reviews by A. Hugh Fisher and Caleb Reade, 1906-1926
      - Notes regarding T. Sturge Moore, 1903-1938 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Obituaries for Frederic Stevens and T. Sturge Moore, 1907, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Poems (manuscripts, tear sheets, and clippings from periodicals), 1896-1929 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Travel writings, published (tear sheets and clippings from periodicals), 1901-1914 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Miscellaneous essays, letters to editors, short stories, and talks, 1896-1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
        Includes autograph manuscripts, typescripts, and clippings
  - Ephemera
    - Ephemera, 1899-1942 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs, 1886-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
- Fine Art, 1881-1941; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series III is organized into four subseries: Drawings, Paintings, Prints, and Reproductions.
  Drawn and etched portraits include Fisher's literary friends Walter de la Mare, George W. Russell ("A.E."), and W. B. Yeats, among others, as well as the author/artist T. Sturge Moore. There are two self-portraits, two portraits of Fisher's second wife Lilias, and two of the printmaker Gyula (Julius) Komjati; many of the prints were inscribed by the artist to Herbert West. The Paintings subseries primarily contains watercolors, with one work in oil, and includes two views of the home of author Margaret Leigh. Box 9 holds two mats specially designed for the watercolors "Rocks at Low Tide" and "Wagon Shed, France" (stored in Box 8; see August 13, 1939, letter from Fisher to West). Prints also holds a series of woodcuts Fisher made to accompany Milton's "Lycidas," which were meant to be published by the Black Cat Press in Chicago; the volume was never issued. The subseries ends with one etching by Gyula Komjati. Reproductions contains photographs and photostats of Fisher's work, as well as some of his illustrations in clippings and tearsheets from publications.
  - Drawings
    - England, 1881, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 63)
      Contains "Cornwall" (1881) and "All Souls" (1940)
    - "The Gods at Golf," illustrated poem, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Portraits, 1919-1941
      Contains Lascelles Abercrombie (1919), Felix Andrews (1938), Gordon Bottomley (1921), Walter de la Mare (undated), A. Hugh Fisher (2 self-portraits, 1938 and 1941), Lilias Fisher (1927), Oscar Levy (1941), T. Sturge Moore (1922), George W. Russell (1934), and W. B. Yeats (1932)
    - Sketches from classical sculptures (2), undated
  - Paintings
    - Coastal scene, watercolor, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Calf, oil on canvas mounted on board, undated
    - Margaret Leigh's home on Bodmin Moor, Cornwall, watercolor (2 scenes), [1936] (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - "Rocks and Low Tide," watercolor on paper, 1939
    - Scenes on Bodmin Moor, Cornwall (3), watercolor on paper mounted on board, undated
    - "Wagon Shed, France," watercolor on board, 1939
  - Prints
    - Birds and animals, 1928, undated
      Contains "Jimmy the puma," "The Shearers," "Spectacled Owls" (1928), "Study of a Long-eared Owl," and "Study of a Rook"
    - Czechoslovakia and Hungary, 1933, undated
      Contains "Budapest Early Morning," "Budapest the Two-fold City," "Coronation Church, Budapest," "Czecho-Slovak peasant" (1933), "Daphnis and Chloe (Czecho-Slovakia)" (2 copies), "Firtrees, Brodyan, Czechoslovakia," "Hungarian Plain," "The Little Carpathians," and "The Mayor's Guard" (1933)
    - England, 1886-1927, undated
      Contains "Looking towards Holmbury from Leith" (1886), "Princes Riseborough in Snow" (1927), and "The Square, Winchester" (undated)
    - "Lycidas" woodcuts made to accompany Milton poem, circa 1923 (Box 6, Folder 67)
      Also contains second set, trial proofs, inscribed to Roger Ingpen; gift of Robert Barry
    - Portraits, 1901-1936, undated
      Contains portraits of Lilias Fisher (titled "The French Hat," 1906), Gyula (Julius) Komjati (2 images, 1933), William F. Revell (2 copies, one titled "Portrait of a Philosopher," 1901), Béla Szylágyi (titled "Hungarian Calvinist Pastor," 1936), and W. B. Yeats
    - "Neer do well," etching by Gyula (Julius) Komjati, undated (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Reproductions
    - Reproductions, 1893-1941 (Box 6, Folder 69)
      Includes contemporary photographs and photostats of Fisher's works, as well as printed reproductions and tear sheets; also includes reproduction of a portrait drawing of Fisher by A. Filmore Valentine
- OVERSIZE
  - Writings: book reviews by A. Hugh Fisher and Caleb Reade (in Series II), 1906-1926 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Writings: travel writings, published (tear sheets and clippings from periodicals) (in Series II), 1910-1913 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Ephemera: music by Jennie La Forge Cutler (in Series II), 1914 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Photograph of Fisher (in Series II), undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Drawings: Portraits (in Series III), 1919-1941 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Drawings: Sketches from classical sculptures (2) (in Series III), undated (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Paintings: Calf (in Series III), undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Paintings: "Rocks and Low Tide" (in Series III), 1939 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Paintings: Scenes on Bodmin Moor, Cornwall (3) (in Series III), undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Paintings: "Wagon Shed, France" (in Series III), 1939 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Prints: Birds and animals (in Series III), 1928, undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Prints: Czechoslovakia and Hungary (in Series III), 1933, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Prints: England (in Series III), 1886-1927, undated (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Prints: Portraits (in Series III), 1901-1936, undated (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Reproductions (in Series III), 1893-1941 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Special mats (2) created for watercolors (in Series III), 1939 (Box 9)